8
19
20
The Experiments
Table of Contents
Arranged Alphabetically by Instrumental Technique
Atomic Spectroscopy 23
Cyclic Voltammetry of Fe(CN)63-/Fe(CN)64- Couple and Evaluation of CV as an Analytical Met
Fluorescence Spectroscopy and A Characterization of Quinine
Fundamentals Investigations of Gas Chromatography
Separation of Urinary Compounds by High Performance Liquid Chromatography
Quantitative Analysis of Xylene Mixtures by Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy
Determination of the Protonation Sequence of Methyliminodiacetic Acid and of the Stoichiometry of the Molybdenum-Methyliminodiacetic Complex by Proton Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy
Analysis of APC Tablets by  A) UV Absorption and Fluorescence Spectrophotometry and B) NMR Spectroscopy
pKa of and Indicator by visible spectroscopy
Graphite Furnace Atomic Absorption
GC-MS
ICP-OES
Cd/Se Quantum Dots
hod 29
35 41 47 51 55 59 65 Handout* Handout* Handout* Handout
*  or worse - verbal instructions! 21
22

Separation of Urinary Compounds by High Performance Liquid Chromatography
Theory: Liquid chromatography involves the partitioning of an analyte between two phases, a mobile phase and a stationary phase.  The chemical identities of these phases dictates the type of chromatography being performed:
Type of Chromatography
Adsorption Partition Ion-Exchange Size Exclusion
Stationary Phase
solid polar material like silica or alumina
solid core has liquid layer coated or chemically bound; must be immiscible with mobile phase
cross-linked polymer beads with charged groups (anionic or cationic forms available)
polymer beads with internal pores of tightly regulated size
Mobile Phase
various depending on relative strengths of solvents and solutes
‘normal’ phase has a nonpolar mobile phase (more polar column). ‘reversed’ phase has a polar mobile phase (less polar column)
ionic buffer solutions
any liquid that does not dissolve the beads nor react analytes
How Separation Occurs
Competitive equilibria where stronger mobile phase drives solutes off stationary phase: too strong yields no separation; too weak yields no elution.
Species dissolve between bound and mobile liquids. A higher affinity for mobile phase yields rapid elution.  Higher affinity for bound yields slower elution.
Competitive equilibria between analytes and buffer components for charged sites on stationary phase.
Species are separated purely on size as they traverse pores. Larger species elute first as they enter fewer pores.
As illustrated by this listing, several different types of chromatography are possible.  All of them share some common attributes.  A sample is injected at the head of a column and driven through by a mobile phase that is usually pumped at moderate to high pressures.  It passes a stationary phase and partitions between the two phases according some degree of separation.  The sample elutes from the tail of the column and solutes are passed by some form of detector.  Final output is sent to integrator or computer for display. As with GC, the are under a peak is proportional to concentration.  For sharp peaks and carefully controlled flow rates, peak heights will also be proportional to concentration.  In either case, a calibration curve is the method of quantitation. In this experiment, the separation of urinary metabolites will be performed by reversed phase chromatography.  The stationary phase packing will be small beads saturated with a chemically bound octadecyl hydrocarbon group (C18).  Nonpolar components, which have a high affinity for the C18 environment, elute with relatively long retention times whereas more polar materials, including ionic species, will elute early.  This experiment illustrates how five clinically important urinary compounds
47
(uracil, uric acid, xanthine, allopurinol, and nicotinamide) can be separated and determined.  The separation is achieved via isocratic elution (same mobile phase throughout) with ultraviolet detection. The order of elution is the same as the order of listing of the five species.
Apparatus: Chemicals:
Experimental
Liquid Chromatograph (Thermo Surveyor PDA system) with 25-ìL sample injection system, UV (254 nm) detection, 30 cm x 4 mm C18 column or whatever is currently available. Volumetric flasks, six 100 mL, one 10 mL Pipets, one 5 mL, four 4 mL, four 3 mL, four 2 mL, four 1 mL Mohr pipet, 2 mL Nalgene membrane filter, 0.2 ìL Several syringe filters Centrifuge
Stock solutions of Uracil, 2.43 mg/100 mL Uric Acid, 11.74 mg/100 mL  - Must be fresh each day! Xanthine, 4.67 mg/100 mL Allopurinol, 5.43 mg/100 mL Nicotinamide, 18.09 mg/100 mL (Made up with doubly distilled water and with several drops of 40% NaOH to enhance solubility; refrigerate until used.) Urine samples Unknown samples that contain the above components (plus uracil) Methanol , HPLC grade in LC solvent bottle Water, HPLC grade in LC solvent bottle 0.05 M acetic acid, buffered to pH 4.5; filtered (0.45 ìm) into solvent bottle ZnSO4 solution, 100 g/L 0.1 M NaOH
Procedures: Instrument Parameters
Mobile phase will be the acetic acid buffer at approximately 2000 psi (or whatever yields 2.0 mL/min). This phase and all solvents must be degassed by helium purge for 15 minutes prior to starting the pump. The absorption maxima reported in the literature2 are uracil, 258 nm; uric acid, 292 nm; xanthine, 267 nm; allopurinol, 251 nm; and nicotinamide, 262 nm.  The literature also reports that 254 nm is effective for detection.  Since the Integral 4000 has a diode array, we can collect spectra for each peak.  The manual has more information.  A method should be prepared to run the 5 standards and 2 samples.
Calibration 48
Uracil is used as an internal standard because of its stability and its short retention time. Pipet 5.00-mL aliquots of the uracil stock solution into each of six 100-mL volumetric flasks.  Into one, pipet 1.00 mL of each of the other four stock solutions.  Similarly pipet 2.00, 3.00, 4.00, and 5.00 mL of each stock solution into four other flasks.  Ask the instructor to place an unknown into the sixth flask. Fill all flasks to the mark with doubly distilled water. Filter a few mL of each solution into an auto sampler vial and firmly attach the top.  Place these into the tray being very careful not to touch the sampler arm (which easily knocks out of calibration costing needles and downtime).  Run the method and collect the print outs.
Urine Sample
Pipet 5.0 mL of urine into a centrifuge tube that contains 15 mL of doubly distilled  water.  Precipitate the urinary proteins by addition of 1.5 mL ZnSO4 solution (100 g/L ) and 0.8 mL of 0.1 M NaOH. Centrifuge (see Dr. H) for 10 minutes at 5000 rpm.  Filter the supernatant liquid through 0.2 ìm Nalgene membrane filter to remove any remaining particulate matter. Dilute 1 mL of the filtrate to 10 mL and inject with no further pretreatment.  Stop the run after 20 minutes of elution time.
After the run, purge the column with 1:1 methanol-water for 20 minutes followed by 20 minutes of pure methanol.
Treatment of Data
Determine the efficiency of the column by calculating the number of theoretical plates (N) using the retention time (tR) and the base peak width (wB):
N  =  16 (tR/wB)2 Typical results for a reverse phase column vary from 1500 to 2000 plates for a flow rate of 2.0 mL/min.
Prepare standard additions working curves for allopurinol, nicotinamide, uric acid, and xanthine (plot all on the same axes).  Determine the components in the unknown and the concentration of each from these curves.  Similarly, identify the individual compounds and their concentrations in the urine sample.
Questions:
1. Are any of the analytes (or other species in unknown) studied in this experiment amenable to separation on an ion-exchange column?  Explain.
Calculate the analytical sensitivities for each analyte compound.  For which species is the HPLC method used in this experiment most sensitive?
Calculate the efficiency of the column for each species as well as the height equivalent to a theoretical plate (see text, class notes, or GC lab for equations).
Explain the function of the mobile phase in GC vs. LC.  Be specific with details - this is not a 1 or 2 point answer!
2. 3. 4.
C C C
49
5. How could this experiment be performed to get better resolution between the peaks for uric acid and uracil?
References:
1. Bastian, D.W., Miller, R.L., Halline, A.G., Senftleber, F.C., and Veening, H.,J. Chem. Ed., 54, 766(1977). 2. Senftleber, F.C., Halline, A.G., Veening, H., and Dayton, D.A., Cl
in. Chem., 22, 1522(1976). 50
Quantitative Analysis of Xylene Mixtures by Fourier Transform Infrared
Theory: Absorption in the infrared region of the spectrum is due to transitions involving vibrational energy levels. By far the most important application of infrared spectroscopy is qualitative analysis.  Functional groups can be identified by their characteristic absorption bands in the infrared.  Also, infrared spectra are unique for a particular compound, which means that if a spectrum for an unknown matches a known spectrum, the unknown has been identified.
For several reasons, infrared absorption is not well suited for quantitative analysis.  Because sources are weak and detectors insensitive, it is necessary to record spectra using wide bandwidths.  Since IR peaks are relatively narrow, this means it is difficult to avoid instrumental deviations from Beer's Law.  Many of these problems have been circumvented by the use of Fourier transform instruments where multiple scans can be rapidly obtained and the signals averaged.  Other problems include solvent absorption and the lack of suitable optical materials for quantitative measurement of absorption.  Since glass and quartz absorb in the IR, it is necessary to use salt plates to make IR cells.  Fixed path cells also assist the chemist in improving the determination.
In this experiment, a quantitative IR analysis of a mixture of xylenes is performed.  This experiment illustrates the use of an internal standard to compensate for some of the measurement problems in the IR. The internal standard is added in equal amount to both standards and sample and their infrared spectra obtained using standard salt plates.  The ratio of absorbance of compounds of interest (m- and p-xylene in this experiment) to internal standard (o-xylene) is measured and compared to absolute absorbance values. The idea is that variations in sample volume, cell transmittance, etc., will affect both internal standard and compound of interest equally, and, therefore, the ratio of absorbances will be independent of these variables. In a second experiment, the same samples spectra will be obtained using a fixed path cell with similar data analysis.
Apparatus: Chemicals:
Experimental
Fourier Transform IR (PE System 400) 2 salt plates and holder Fixed path cell Disposable pipets Luer-lock syringe without needle
cyclohexane o-, m-, p- xylene Methylene chloride or chloroform for cleaning salt plates between trials
Procedure:
C
Prepare, in 10 mL volumetric flasks, eight standard solutions all of which have a composition consisting of 20.0% by volume o-xylene and using cyclohexane as solvent with 0.0, 5.0, 10.0, 15.0, 20.0, 25.0, 30.0, and 35.0% by volume of both standards m-xylene and p-xylene.  (I.e.  the last sample has 35.0 % m-
51
C C C C •
xylene, 35.0 % p-xylene, 20.0 % o-xylene, and made to mark with cyclohexane.)
Obtain an unknown consisting of a mixture of m-xylene and p-xylene in cyclohexane.  Return it to the refrigerator after use.  Record the unknown number!
Pipet 2 mL of o-xylene internal standard into a 10 mL volumetric and dilute to the mark with unknown. (Use Pasteur pipet to dilute.)
Using a Pasteur pipet, place two drops of the standard solution between the salt plates. (Caution: the salt plates are easily etched by moisture on your hands.  Hold them by the edges and rinse them thoroughly with methylene chloride between samples and when finished.  Store in a desiccator.) Record the spectra of the standards and unknown using the available Fourier transform infrared instrument.  Keep in mind that data analysis requires being able to measure absorbances.  If the absorbance peaks are too large - this operation can not be accomplished.  Recently using a PE 2000, all samples had to be diluted 1:10 to accomplish this analysis!
Obtain the spectra of the standards and samples using a fixed pathlength liquid cell.  This cell must be loaded with a needle-less luer lock syringe obtained from the instructor.  The faces of this cell are again made of salt and the same rules as above still apply.   Between trials, flush with methylene chloride.
All spectra should be save in a directory named after your lab group (limited to 8 characters of course). When you are done with the lab, all files should be deleted from the hard drive.
Using one (1, uno, singular) sample, run a single scan vs a single background scan, 10 scans vs 10 background scans, and 100 scans vs. 100 background scans.  Compare the signal to noise ratio relative to number of scans.  Report and discuss this in your report.
Treatment of Data:   The bands used for the analysis are:
o-xylene 13.5 microns (micrometers) m-xylene 13.0 or 14.5 microns p-xylene 12.6 microns
Use the instruments computer to obtain the absorbance values at the above frequencies (what are these frequencies in wavenumbers?)
Plot working curves of both absorbance of each standard and the ratio of the absorbance of the desired constituent to that of the internal standard versus concentration (in %) for both sample holders. Determine the composition of the unknown using these curves.
Compare the two sample holders.  Is it necessary or desirable to use the internal standard approach with both, either, or neither of the sample holders.  Comment.
Questions:
52
1. How does a dispersive IR instrument differ from a Fourier transform IR instrument?  Include both instrumental differences and relative advantages/disadvantages.
2. What are the specific advantages and disadvantages of a double-beam dispersive instrument vs a single beam dispersive instrument?  With this in mind, why don’t companies make a double beam Fourier transform instrument?
3. Discuss the particular advantages of optics such as beam splitters for infrared instruments: NaCl, KBr, CaF2, LiF, CaBr2, and quartz.  Compare specifically such quantities as useful wavelength range and resolution.
4. Historically, IR has been plagued by poor stability of sources and detectors.  Based on your results, does the PE FTIR suffer from the difficulties?   This is not a simple yes/no question. Explain!
53
54
Determination of the Protonation Sequence of Methyliminodiacetic Acid and of the Stoichiometry of the Molybdenum-Methyliminodiacetic Complex by Proton NMR
Overall Theory:5 Methyliminodiacetic acid (MIDA) is a metal complexing agent similar to EDTA, with three acidic protons.  Using the relative acidity of these protons, the identities of the peaks in the NMR spectrum can be determined.  In addition, the stoichiometry of the Mo(Vl) complex of MIDA will be de- termined by observing NMR line shifts as a function of pH or Mo(VI) concentration.
Apparatus Chemicals
Experimental
NMR spectrometer NMR tubes (8) Pipets (2), 1 mL Disposable pipets and bulbs Beakers, ten 10 mL, one 25 mL
0.5 M MIDA in D2O, 15 mL 0.5 M sodium molybdate [Na2MoO4] in D2O, 10 mL 6.0 M hydrochloric acid [HCI] in D2O 6.O M sodium hydroxide [NaOH] in D2O t-Butyl alcohol, a few drops per NMR tube
pH paper (pH I to 12) or pH meter
Part I:  Determination of the MIDA Spectrum
Theory: At pH 0, MIDA is fully protonated.
CH2COOH
+ / CH 3 )N)H \ CH2COOH
Because both the carboxylic acid and amine protons are acidic, incremental addition of base will cause sequential chemical shifts of the neighboring C)H protons.  Knowing the relative acidities of these two groups (remember Quant??) the C)H proton peaks can be assigned.  The experiment can also be performed in the reverse where the chemical shift data can be used to assign relative acidities of the groups.  This is useful when two identical groups are present with different pKa's (several amino acids come to mind).
5  The theory behind NMR was covered in 52-232, Organic 2, and will not be covered here.  The instructor has suggestions of texts one can read to review NMR theory starting with chapter 19 of Skoog, Holler, and Nieman.
55
Remember, the chemical shift is directly related to the electron density around the nucleus. Procedure:
Take about 15 mL of 0.5 M MIDA stock solution and pipet I mL into a 10-mL beaker.  By use of 6 M HCI or 6 M NaOH dissolved in D2O (minimize exposure to air which will lead to a huge water raman line), adjust the pH of the MIDA solution to zero.  Add 1 mL of 0.5 M MIDA to each of two other 10-mL beakers.   Adjust the pH of the second to pH 6 and of the third to pH 12. Add a few drops of t-butyl alcohol to each beaker.   Fill three 5-mm NMR tubes to a depth of about 50 mm with the various MIDA solutions and record their spectra. Set t-butyl alcohol as the 0.0 ppm shift.  How many peaks do you expect to see?  Make sure you have spectra where the peaks of interest are large enough to see and measure!
Treatment of Data:
Assign all peaks observed in the spectra of MIDA by observing the change in each peaks chemical shift as the pH is changed.  Remember that butyl alcohol, not TMS, was used as the reference.
1. 2.
Questions: Why are fewer peaks seen in the spectra of MIDA than could be expected? How do the assigned peaks chemical shifts compare to those measured with TMS as the reference?
Part II:  Determination of the Stoichiometry of the Mo-MIDA Complex Theory:
Below pH 8, Mo(Vl) forms a complex with MIDA.  By recording spectra of solutions with fixed amounts of Mo(Vl) and varying amounts of MIDA, the stoichiometry for the complex can be determined using peak assignments made in part 1.  Each peak above illustrates its characteristic shielding depending on if the neighboring site is occupied or vacant.  With these assignments, the determination of the stoichiometry and structure of the complex should be easily determined. You are encouraged to set up models and/or tables to assist in this determination.  Make sure your spectral output is large enough for you to see each applicable peak!
Procedure:
Obtain 10 mL of 0.5 M Na2MoO4 stock solution, and five more 10-mL beakers.  Use the remaining 0.5 M MIDA stock solution to pipet the amounts of MIDA and Mo(VI) listed in table 1.  Add a few drops of t- butyl alcohol to each.  Fill five NMR  tubes (as above) with the solutions and record their spectra.
Table 1 56
Beaker 1 2 3 4 5
Stoichiometry Mo:MIDA
1 : 0.5 1 : 1 1 : 1.5 1 : 2 1 : 3
Na2MoO4 (mL)
2 1 2 1 1
MIDA (mL)
1 1 3 2 3
1. 2. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5.
Treatment of Data: What is the stoichiometry of the MO-MIDA complex?  Explain. Ouestions:
Some of the spectra obtained in Part II contain no excess MIDA.  A comparison of the spectra of bound MIDA and free MIDA (as seen in Part I) shows remarkable differences, including a change in the number of peaks.  Explain why the bound and free MIDA exhibit different spectra, remembering that two protons in the same magnetic environment will give only one peak. (Hint: Make a model of the free MIDA and of the Mo-MIDA complex.) Does molybdenum bind to the nitrogen or carboxylate groups of MI DA, or does it bind to all three groups?
Illustrate the Mo-MIDA complex as you have described it above. References:
J. W. Akitt, "N.M.R. and Chemistry; An Introduction to Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy," Chapman and Hall, London, 1973.
S. I. Chan, R. J. Kula, and D. T. Sawyer, JACS, 1964, 86, 377. L. V. Haynes and D. T. Sawyer, Inorganic Chem., 1967, 6, 2146. R. J. Kula, D. T. Sawyer, S. I. Chan, and C. M. Finley, JACS, 1963, 85, 2930. R. J. Kula and D. T. Sawyer, Inorganic Chem., 1964, 3, 458.
57
58
Analysis of APC Tablets by A)  UV Absorption and Fluorescence Spectrophotometry B) NMR Spectroscopy
Part A Theory:
This experiment illustrates solvent extraction, a method for separating substances that would otherwise interfere in an analysis.  The analyte has three components (aspirin, caffeine, and phenacetin) and can not be analyzed spectroscopically due to severe overlap of the absorption peaks.   In a solvent extraction the sample is dissolved and shaken with a two-phase solvent system.  Solutes will partition between the two phases according to their relative solubilities in the two solvents.  In favorable cases, an interferent will go essentially completely into one phase while the solute of interest stays in the other.  In this experiment aspirin (acetylsalicylic acid) can be extracted from methylene chloride into aqueous bicarbonate buffer because at the pH of the bicarbonate, aspirin is ionic and favors the more polar aqueous phase.  After acidification, the aspirin is no longer ionic and ion can be extracted back into chloroform.  The other two components, caffeine and phenacetin, are unaffected by bicarbonate and will remain exclusively in the organic layer.  Considerable care must be exercised to perform an extraction properly!
UV-visible absorption spectrometry can be applied to the analysis of a mixture of two components left in the original organic layer, caffeine and phenacetin.  These still have overlapping absorption spectra. The analysis is done by measuring the absorbance at two wavelengths,  ë 1 and  ë 2. Since the absorbances of the two components C and P are additive:
A 1 = å C 1 bC C  +  å P 1 bC P
A 2 =  å C 2 bC C  +  å P 2 bC P
where b is the pathlength, and A 1 and A 2 are the absorbances at ë 1 and ë 2 respectively. The molar absorptivities  å C 1, å P 1,  å C 2 and  å P 2 are determined using standard solutions. This yields two equations which can be solved for the two unknown concentrations, C C and C P. Best results are obtained when ë 1 and ë 2 are chosen so that there is a large difference in molar absorptivities at each wavelength and one compound absorbs more strongly at ë 1 while the other absorbs more strongly at ë 2.
The Varian Cary 5000 is a high resolution double beam UV-VIS-NIR spectrophotometer. The Spectronic 20, used in previous courses, is a single beam VIS instrument. The Cary has several features which make it a more versatile and precise instrument.  A typical double beam instrument has two sources, a D2 lamp for measurements in the UV and a W lamp for the visible and the near infrared.  This Cary has an added line source - a mercury vapor lamp for low level work in the UV.  It has a photomultiplier tube detector for measuring low light levels.  Quartz optics permit measurements at wavelengths in the UV down to 180 nm. Another feature of the high resolution instruments are variable slits, making it possible to work at narrow bandwidths. The Cary is a ratio-recording spectrophotometer. The electronics in the instrument measure the intensities of the reference and sample beams. The ratio is then displayed on the monitor.  Cost for this much technology - list price is around $60K.
The aspirin will be analyzed via fluorescence spectrophotometry.  In fluorescence, the electronically excited state produced by absorption of a photon rapidly returns to ground state. In some molecules this
59
relaxation process is accompanied by the emission of a photon. The resulting light is called fluorescence. At low concentrations fluorescence intensity is proportional to concentration and can be used for analysis. In this experiment the aspirin is hydrolyzed in base using yielding the fluorescent salicylate anion. The aspirin concentration is determined by comparing analyte fluorescence to fluorescence intensity from a standard salicylate solution.  Aspirin fluorescence will be measured using the brand spanking new PE LS-55 Spectrofluorometer (ca $20K)
Apparatus: Chemicals:
Experimental A
UV-Vis spectrophotometer (Cary 5000) Spectrofluorometer (PE LS-55) Quartz UV-Vis and fluorescence cuvettes 100 mL separatory funnel Assorted volumetric flasks
Solid aspirin, caffeine, and phenacetin Methylene chloride 1% aqueous sodium carbonate solution (or ingredients) 0.5 M aqueous NaOH
Procedure: Each Group:
C C C C C
Accurately weigh out about 0.1 g of the APC (aspirin, phenacetin, caffeine) powder into a 50 mL beaker.
Add 20 mL of methylene chloride, then transfer the mixture to a 100-mL separatory funnel, rinsing all undissolved particles into the funnel with more methylene chloride.
Extract the methylene chloride solution with two separate 10 mL portions of 1% Na2CO3 and with a 5 mL portion of deionized H2O. (Translation: add 10 mL of the carbonate solution to the separatory funnel and shake with occasional venting.  Allow it to separate and remove each layer (due to densities) into separate containers.  Return the organic layer to the funnel and add fresh carbonate.  Repeat operation for deionized water.)   Combine all three aqueous extracts and wash with three 5 mL portions of fresh methylene chloride.  (Consider: which is denser, methylene chloride or 1% carbonate!)  Combine all the organic layers and label as concentrated UV sample.
After washing, pour the Na2CO3 solution into a 50-mL volumetric flask and add 20 mL of 0.5 M NaOH, then dilute to the mark with deionized H2O. Shake well.  Label this as concentrated aspirin.  Perform a 1:250 dilution using 1% Na2CO3 as the diluent.  Shake well.  You will use this latter solution with the fluorometer.
Filter the methylene chloride solution from concentrated UV sample through paper previously wet with methylene chloride into a 50-mL volumetric flask. Dilute to the mark with methylene chloride, further dilute a 2 mL aliquot in a 100-mL volumetric.
Aspirin Group: 60
C
Prepare a standard solution of aspirin using 1% sodium carbonate as the solvent system.  From this, prepare a series of standards that are within the PE LS-55's  linear dynamic range (this can be a challenge!).  Use one to determine the excitation and emission wavelengths for aspirin printing out a combined spectra for your report.  Prepare a calibration curve and measure the fluorescence of each of the unknown solutions.  Plot the fluorescence calibration curve for aspirin and determine the amount of aspirin in the sample correcting for dilution.
Phenacetin/Caffeine Group: C Prepare stock solutions and dilute appropriately to determine the lambda max values for phenacetin and caffeine using the Varian Cary 5000 Spectrophotometer.  Check with the instructor/consultant prior to going further.  Spectra of each species should be exported to Excel for the notebooks and reports.  It is also advisable to obtain the spectrum of aspirin (borrow some from the aspirin group) in case the extraction step was determined to be in error.
C
Prepare 4-5 standards of each compound and measure their absorbances at both lambda max values  Also measure absorbances for all extracted methylene chloride solutions at both wavelengths.  Use the simultaneous dual Beer’s law expressions to calculate the amount of caffeine and phenacetin in the powder sample.  Don’t forget to correct for dilution!
Treatment of Data:
Calculate the percentages of aspirin, phenacetin, and caffeine.  Report the results as a percentage of total mass.  (The total will probably be less than 100% since pharmaceutical preparations frequently contain starch or other inert material as a binder.)  Include the class average and error analysis.
Questions:
1) Obtain structures of the three analytes and indicate why we can remove aspirin from the other two.  Can you suggest a method to separate phenacetin and caffeine in large quantities?
2) Looking at the structure of aspirin - is it logical that it fluoresces?  Explain.
3) A similar product containing caffeine, acetaminophen, and ibuprofen was introduced to market several years ago.   Would this same type of experiment work with a CAI tablet?  Why/Why not?
NMR group: Part B Theory:   Relative amounts of caffeine, phenacetin and aspirin can be determined by either of two methods: (1) by standard comparison, using the caffeine standard to calibrate the integrator; or (2) by the absolute method, using only the spectrum of the unknown and determining the relative percentage of each component by weight, normalizing so that the total percentage equals 100%.
61
Experimental B
Apparatus: proton nmr spectrometer nmr tubes (2), 5 mm microspatula that fits into an nmr tube (can be made by pounding a copper wire)
Chemicals: deuterated chloroform tetramethysilane [TMS] (1%) in deuterated chloroform aspirin, 20 to 40 mg per tube in 1 mL of 1% TMS; sealed and labeled caffeine, 20 to 40 mg per tube in 1 mL of 1% TMS; sealed and labeled phenacetin, 20 to 40 mg per tube in 1 mL of 1% TMS; sealed and labeled APC tablet, finely ground (Use no more than 100 mg for analysis due to solubility of aspirin in chloroform.)
Procedures: Read the specific operating instructions for the Bruker AC200 spectrometer.  Use ethylbenzene to make sure the instrument is on scale and working properly.
C
Three color coded tubes containing 20 to 40 mg of each of the three components and TMS in CDCl3 have been prepared.  The spectrum and the integral of the spectrum of the contents of each tube should be taken.  Examination of these spectra will allow suitably non-overlapping peaks to be chosen for the quantitative analysis of each component in the APC tablet.
C
Clean two nmr tubes by rinsing several times with chloroform.  Into one tube, accurately weigh (to 0.1 mg) approximately 100 mg of the APC tablet powder.  Do not exceed 100 mg because aspirin is only slightly soluble in chloroform.  Into the other tube, weigh accurately (to 0.1 mg) approximately 50 mg of pure caffeine.  To each tube add 1 mL of 1% TMS (CDCl3) and immediately close both tubes. Using the caffeine standard just prepared, adjust sensitivity and resolution of the instrument. Take a spectrum and integral of the known caffeine solution. As quickly as possible and without changing any instrument parameters, replace the caffeine tube with the unknown tube, scan and integrate.
Treatment of Data:   From the spectra of the three components, determine which peaks in the unknown belongs to which component and determine the number of protons per peak.  Select peaks for each component to be used for the quantitative analysis. Determine the relative amounts of caffeine, phenacetin, and aspirin (by percent weight) by two methods:
1. Standard comparison method.  Use the caffeine standard to calibrate the integrator and determine the percent of each component. 2. Absolute method.  Using only the spectrum of the unknown, determine the relative percent of each component by weight, normalized so that the sum of the three percents adds to 100%.
Questions:
1. Evaluate NMR as a technique for the determination of aspirin at a trace level.  How does it compare with other analytical techniques such as fluorescence, UV-visible spectroscopy, and liquid chromatography?
2. Compare and discuss the APC tablet results from the two parts of this experiment.
62
References: For UV method of APC analysis: TV Parke, AM Ridbey, EE Kennedy, and WW Hilty, Anal. Chem., 1951, 23, 953.
For an IR method of APC analysis: M Jones and RL Thatcher, Anal. Chem., 1951, 23, 957.
For a NMR method of APC analysis: DB Hollis, Anal. Chem., 1963, 35, 1682.
63
64
The pKa of an Indicator UV Absorption Spectrophotometry
The use of spectrophotometry for the evaluation of the pKa of an acid-base indicator is demonstrated in this experiment.
Part A Theory:
This lab is written to present a challenge to the chemist.  The theory and the experimental set-up are all aimed at bromothymol blue (3’,3”-dibromothymolsulfone-phthalein), a member of a large class of acid-base indicators known as “sulfone-phthaleins”.  However, you will be assigned a different indicator in probably a different class and will need to consider how to adapt the experiment for that different dye!  Be sure to start early so you don’t finish late!  It is also imperative to keep in mind the goals of the experiment as well as data reduction. Bromothymol blue has three possible forms depending on pH:
The equilibrium between the yellow acid form (HIn -) and the royal-blue basic form (In 2-) can be represented as
HIn -  +  H2O   º   H3O +  +  In 2- (1)
and the equilibrium constant for the acid dissociation is
Ka  =  AH3O+ AIn2-  / AHIn- (2)
where A refers to the activity. Converting to logarithmic form and rearranging terms yields
pH  =  pKa  +  log ( A In2-  / A HIn- ). (3)
65
Since activity is directly related to concentration by activity coefficient fi, this expression can be expressed as
pH  =  pKa  +  log ([In 2-] / [HIn -])  + log  (f In2- / f HIn-) . (4)
The ratio of activity coefficients may be incorporated into the equilibrium constant to give
pH  =  pK’a  +  log ([In 2-] / [HIn -]) (5)
where pK’a is an apparent indicator constant (2).  Thus a plot of pH vs  log ([In 2-] / [HIn -]) should give a straight line with an intercept (at which [In 2-] = [HIn -]) equal to pK’a. In this experiment, the indicator bromothymol blue is dissolved in a series of buffer solutions of known pH.  The ration [In 2-] / [HIn -] is then measured spectrophotometrically and pK’a is calculated from a plot of
equation 5.
Apparatus: Spectrophotometer Cuvettes (2) Pipets,   1 mL, 5 mL, and 10 mL Beaker (3),  100 mL Volumetric flasks (4), 25 mL
Chemicals: indicator such as bromothymol blue, 0.1% in ethanol 0.10 M sodium hydrogen phosphate 0.10 M potassium dihydrogen phosphate Hydrochloric acid (conc) 4 M sodium hydroxide
Procedures note: Bromothymol blue is unstable in acid media over prolonged periods of time.  Therefore, obtain all absorbance measurements with a solution on the same afternoon that you prepare the solution.
A.  Absorption Spectra of Bromothymol Blue at Various pH Values
1. pH . 1.  Carefully pipet 1 mL of bromothymol blue stock solution into a clean 25-mL volumetric flask.  Add a few milliliters of distilled water, then 4 drops of concentrated HCl, and finally dilute to the mark with distilled water.  Transfer some to a cuvette and obtain an absorption spectrum between 350 and 600 nm..
pH . 6.9.  Pipet 1 mL of indicator in a 25-mL volumetric flask and add 5 mL each of 0.10 M Na2HPO4 and KH2PO4 from a pipet.  Dilute to the mark and obtain the spectrum.
2.
pH . 13.  To 1 mL of indicator in a 25-mL volumetric flask, add 12 drops of 4 M NaOH. Dilute to the mark and obtain the spectrum.
3.
The three curves, when plotted on a single axis should intersect each other at a single point, called an isosbestic point.
66
B.  Absorbance of Solutions (Differing in pH) at Selected Wavelengths
Refer to the graph you have made and select two wavelengths at which further absorbance measurements will be made.  You should select a wavelength to the left of the isosbestic point and one to the right of this point.  Choose wavelengths where the acid and base forms of the indicator show a maximum difference in their absorbance. Measurements will be made on solutions with seven different pH values other than the three solutions studied thus far.
mL indicator mL H2PO4 - mL HPO4 2- pH
1. 1.0 5.0 0.0 ~4.5
2. 1.0 5.0 1.0 6.2
3. 1.0 10.0 5.0 ?
4. 1.0 5.0 10.0 ?
5. 1.0 1.0 5.0 ?
6. 1.0 1.0 10.0 ?
7. 1.0 0.0 5.0 ~9.1
Pipet the above quantities for a given pH into a 25-mL volumetric flask and dilute to the mark. Measure the absorbance of each solution at the two selected wavelengths.  Remember to readjust the instrument to 0 and 100%T whenever you change the wavelength setting.  Alternatively, it can be very effective to scan each sample and extract the absorbance information from the plot. Calculate the pH of the above solutions given the fact that the second ionization constant for phosphoric acid is 1.3 x 10 -7 (pK2 = 6.89).  Alternatively, pH values can be measured by a pH meter.
Treatment of Data CAUTION:   This is written for the experiment enclosed.  Since you used a different indicator (unless Dr. H has turned into a wimp), your pH values will be different and you will need to THINK about the data reduction!
Combining the absorbance values at the two selected wavelengths (obtained in Procedure A) with the data obtained in Procedure B, plot absorbance vs. pH for each of the two wavelengths studied.  The midpoint of each curve corresponds to equal concentrations of the acid and of the base forms of the indicator.  From each graph, determine the pK’a of the indicator. Draw two horizontal lines across each of your  A vs. pH plots; one corresponding to the absorbance of the acid form of the indicator and the other corresponding to base form of the indicator.  Any deviation of the actual absorbance from these two lines is a measure of the extent to which one form or the other has been converted to the other form. Consider the absorbance reading obtained for the pH 6.2 solution (figure 2).  By subtracting the absorbance at 6.2 from the absorbance at pH 1, a measure of the amount of In 2- in the solution at pH 6.2 can be obtained.  By subtracting the absorbance at pH 13 from the absorbance
67
at pH 6.2 a comparable measure of the amount of HIn - in the pH 6.2 solution can be obtained. The ratio of In 2- to HIn - can then be found.  The ratio also can be found by measuring with a ruler the relative lengths of the two arrows indicated in figure 2. Determine the In 2-/ HIn - ratio that corresponds to each of the points plotted on one of your two absorbance vs. pH graphs, and plot log In 2- / HIn - vs. pH.  That point where the line crosses the vertical axis at zero concentration corresponds to equal concentrations of the acid and base forms thus we can obtain the pK’a.  Report all three values for pK’a.
Discussion must include comparisons to literature values for the pKa as well as consideration of the color change range.  You should also consider how you performed the experiment and include changes you would make in the procedure based on your experience.
Figure 2:  Absorption of  an acid-base indicator as a function of pH
Questions 1   a b
c d 2
What is meant by an isosbestic point? If the molar absorptivities of HIn - and of In 2- were determined at a wavelength corresponding to an isosbestic point, how would they compare in value? What factors could contribute to the inability of an operator to obtain an isosbestic point in a study of this nature? Could this experiment be applied to an indicator for which no isosbestic point was obtained in the available spectral range?  Explain briefly.
If you were given a series of your indicator solutions of varying pH and were asked to
68
determine the total amount of indicator present in each solution, how would you choose wavelengths and how would you perform the analysis?  (ps, a pH meter is not available)
Suppose the indicator under study  were a dibasic acid which dissociated according to the general equation:
H2In  +  2 H2O   º   2 H3O +  +  In 2-
with both hydrogens coming off simultaneously in a single step (a rare case).
If log (In 2- / H2In) were plotted against pH, what would the slope of the resulting line be? When the line crosses the zero axis, does pH = pKa?  (Show your reasoning).
4 If the indicator dissociated according to the general equation (not a rare case)
(HIn)2   +  2 H2O   º   2 H3O +  +  2 In -
what would you plot in order to get a straight line, and what would the slope of the line be?  (Show your reasoning).
Reference books list the range of bromothymol blue as an indicator from pH 6.0 to 7.8. Can you account for the difference between the true pKa and the “apparent” pK’a deduced from this range?
Outline how would perform this experiment to find both pKa values for a diprotic indicator like  m-Cresol Purple.  Be sure to include both “procedures” as well as pH’s for procedure B.
3
a b
5 6 69
